<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;GA on महाभारते विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/mahAbhAratam/meta/articles/GA/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;GA on महाभारते विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/mahAbhAratam/meta/articles/GA/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>BhIShma parashurAma yuddham</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/mahAbhAratam/meta/articles/GA/bhIShma-parashurAma-yuddham/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/mahAbhAratam/meta/articles/GA/bhIShma-parashurAma-yuddham/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://x.com/GhorAngirasa/status/1793858605604888706&#34;&gt;TW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Bhīṣma was literally protected by 8 divine Brāhmaṇas during the battle &amp;amp; they tell him in a dream that night that he is like their own body &amp;amp; they will protect him from Paraśurāma &amp;amp; give him the Prasvapna mantra (which makes the victim sleep).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;During the battle next day, Bhīṣma is unable to secure any advantage over Paraśurāma (&amp;amp; vice-versa) &amp;amp; decides to end the stalemate by invoking the Prasvapna mantra. Nārada &amp;amp; other Ṛṣis ask him to not use the mantra as it will amount to humiliation of one’s own Guru.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hero types</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/mahAbhAratam/meta/articles/GA/hero-types/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/mahAbhAratam/meta/articles/GA/hero-types/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://x.com/GhorAngirasa/status/1997958577466855580&#34;&gt;TW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Many ways to be a hero&amp;ndash;One of my favorite passages from the Mahābhārata&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When Yudhiṣṭhira asks Bhīṣma (who is on his death-bed made of arrows) about, among several other things, the puṇya gained by a śūra (hero) who does not flee from battle, Bhīṣma proceeds to answer this volley of queries; and when he comes to the subject of heroes, he expands Yudhiṣṭhira’s narrowly phrased question (which restricts the ambit of “śūra” to the warrior on the battlefield) and utters these beautiful ślokas:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>shiva-bhArata: GA</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/mahAbhAratam/meta/articles/GA/shiva-bhAratam/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/mahAbhAratam/meta/articles/GA/shiva-bhAratam/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;(Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://threader.app/thread/1207868863863328768&#34;&gt;https://threader.app/thread/1207868863863328768&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In this sacred time of the year, we dedicate to शिव this thread about the role in the महाभारत of his particular form as श्रीकण्ठ-रुद्र.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;वयस&#34;&gt;व्यासः&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;To add another point, after शिवसहस्रनाम was revealed by कृष्ण to युधिष्ठिर, different sages come to speak of the glory of worshipping शिव &amp;amp; among them, पराशर-ऋषि stated that he worshipped महादेव for a son who will be a वेदव्यास &amp;amp; शिव blesses him with more than what he asked. Not only will he become a वेदव्यास (वेदानां च स वै वक्ता) but will also be 1 of the सप्त-ऋषि in the era of सावर्ण-मनु (सावर्णस्य मनोः सर्गे सप्तर्षिश्च भविष्यति), the author of an इतिहास &amp;amp; पुराण-s (इतिहासस्य कर्ता च पुत्रस्ते जगतो हितः) &amp;amp; wait, relevances to महाभारत? महादेव also gives a specific blessing that this son of पराशर-ऋषि will be a generator of the lineage of कुरु (कुरुवंशकर), although this was not specifically sought by the ऋषि. And indeed, व्यास revived the line of कुरु at a most critical time!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
