<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;Articles on महाभारते विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/mahAbhAratam/meta/articles/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;Articles on महाभारते विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 26 Dec 2013 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/mahAbhAratam/meta/articles/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Battle summary</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/mahAbhAratam/meta/articles/battle-summary/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/mahAbhAratam/meta/articles/battle-summary/</guid>
      <description>Source: TW
(Threads for remaining days are hard to compile due to two thread discontinuities.) Author: Saiswaroopa
Day 01 Could record two general battles and 26 duels on Day One. Only 6 of those duels ended decisively. Pandava side suffered horribly in the hands of Bhishma. Uttara killed in the hands of Shalya. Saving grace being Abhimanyu countering Bhishma and winning over Brihadbala. Another highlight is the maternal grandfather of the Pandavas, Kuntibhoja successfully repelling Vinda-Anuvinda of Avanti and the sons of Draupadi excelling.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>daxa-yAga</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/mahAbhAratam/meta/articles/daxa-yAgaH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/mahAbhAratam/meta/articles/daxa-yAgaH/</guid>
      <description>Source: TW
In the Mahābhārata account of the destruction of Dakṣayāga, Devī is not Dakṣa’s daughter but appears to be Pārvati. Having been cut off from any yajñabhāga, Devī, as if she was an ordinary wife on earth, lamentingly “taunts” Bhagavān about His being disrespected by Dakṣa.
देव्युवाच
किं नाम दानं नियमं तपो वा
कुर्यामहं येन पतिर्ममाद्य।
लभेत भागं च तथैव सर्वं
प्रभुर् विभुश्चाहवनीय एषः।
लभेत भागं भगवानचिन्त्यो
ह्यर्धं तथा भागमथो तृतीयम्॥ 12-290-23</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>DVG: Characters</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/mahAbhAratam/meta/articles/DVG_characters/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/mahAbhAratam/meta/articles/DVG_characters/</guid>
      <description>Source: Sandeep on Prexaa
Characters of the Mahabharata
0 An Introduction to DVG&amp;rsquo;s Monograph ONE OF DVG’s lesser-known works of non-fiction is a sublime bouquet of literary essays innocuously titled Kāvya-svārasya or The Delights of Poetry. However, this rather bland title nicely conceals a veritable treasure-chest filled with invaluable rubies on an astonishing gamut of meditative expositions on the purpose of literature, the nature of talent, contemplations on Rasa, the function of poetry, the triad of aesthetics, elucidations on Joy and a superb investigation into the inner human impulse that creates poetry.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Homeric similarities</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/mahAbhAratam/meta/articles/homeric-similarities/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/mahAbhAratam/meta/articles/homeric-similarities/</guid>
      <description>Source: TW
That the Mahābhārata is concomitant wtih the Iliad can be seen through narrative parallels. Any rapprochment need not imply a direct derivation of one from the other, but it may point to a common kernel between both.
One such association can be seen between Agamemnon &amp;amp; Duryodhana. As aforementioned, the two warriors Agamemnon &amp;amp; Duryodhana share similar narrative stories within either plot including but not limited to: reprehensible behavior to the goddess&amp;rsquo; sons, abjure the advice of elders, commit malfeasances on women, offending the auguries of seers.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ವಾಲ್ಮೀಕಿಮುನಿಗಳ ವಾಗ್ವಿಲಾಸ</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/mahAbhAratam/meta/articles/idioms/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/mahAbhAratam/meta/articles/idioms/</guid>
      <description>Source: prekshaa series
[[ವಾಲ್ಮೀಕಿಮುನಿಗಳ ವಾಗ್ವಿಲಾಸ	Source: prekshaa]]
ತಮೃಷಿಂ ಮನುಷ್ಯಲೋಕಪ್ರವೇಶವಿಶ್ರಾಮಶಾಖಿನಂ ವಾಚಾಮ್ ।
ಸುರಲೋಕಾದವತಾರಪ್ರಾಂತರಖೇದಚ್ಛಿದಂ ವಂದೇ ॥
(ಅನರ್ಘರಾಘವ, ೧.೧೦)
(ಮಾತು ದೂರದ ದೇವಲೋಕದಿಂದ ಜೀವಲೋಕಕ್ಕೆ ನೀರು-ನೆರಳಿಲ್ಲದ ಕಷ್ಟದ ಹಾದಿಯಲ್ಲಿ ಹಾಯ್ದುಬರುವಾಗ ಅದಕ್ಕೆ ನೆಮ್ಮದಿಯ ವಿಶ್ರಾಂತಿವೃಕ್ಷವಾಗಿ ಪರಿಣಮಿಸಿದ ಆದಿಕವಿಗೆ ವಂದನೆಗಳು.)
ರಾಮಾಯಣದ ಸ್ವಾರಸ್ಯಗಳು ನೂರಾರು; ಅವುಗಳಲ್ಲೊಂದು ನುಡಿಬೆಡಗು. ಮಾತಿನ ಈ ಪರಿಯ ಸೊಗಸಾದರೋ ಸಮಷ್ಟಿರೂಪದಲ್ಲಿ ರಸವಾಗಿ, ವ್ಯಷ್ಟಿರೂಪದಲ್ಲಿ ವಕ್ರೋಕ್ತಿಯಾಗಿ ಪರಿಣಮಿಸುತ್ತದೆ. ಇಂಥ ವಕ್ರೋಕ್ತಿಯು ವಾಕ್ಯದ ಸ್ತರದಲ್ಲಿ ಅರ್ಥಾಲಂಕಾರದ ಸೊಬಗನ್ನು ಪಡೆದರೆ, ಪದಗಳ ಮತ್ತು ವಾಕ್ಯಖಂಡಗಳ ಸ್ತರದಲ್ಲಿ ಶಬ್ದಾಲಂಕಾರದ ಹಾಗೂ ನುಡಿಗಟ್ಟುಗಳ ಚೆಲುವನ್ನು ತಳೆಯುತ್ತದೆ. ಶಬ್ದಾಲಂಕಾರಗಳನ್ನು ಬದಿಗಿರಿಸಿದರೆ ಈ ಹಂತದಲ್ಲಿ ನಮಗುಳಿಯುವುದು ನುಡಿಗಾರಿಕೆಯ ಅಂದ. ಇದು ಸಾಭಿಪ್ರಾಯವಿಶೇಷಣವಾಗಿ (ಧ್ವನಿಪೂರ್ಣವಾದ ವಿಶೇಷಣ), ವಾಚೋಯುಕ್ತಿಯಾಗಿ (ನುಡಿಗಟ್ಟು ಅಥವಾ ಇಡಿಯಮ್), ಸಾಮತಿ-ಗಾದೆಮಾತುಗಳಾಗಿ, ನಾಟುನುಡಿಯಾಗಿ ಹತ್ತಾರು ಬಗೆಯಿಂದ ವಿಸ್ತರಿಸಿಕೊಳ್ಳುತ್ತದೆ.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
