<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;० on महाभारते विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/mahAbhAratam/vyAsaH/shlokashaH/bhagavad-gItA-parva/meta/abhinavagupta-gItArtha-sangrahaH/0/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;० on महाभारते विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/mahAbhAratam/vyAsaH/shlokashaH/bhagavad-gItA-parva/meta/abhinavagupta-gItArtha-sangrahaH/0/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Boudon Torzsok</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/mahAbhAratam/vyAsaH/shlokashaH/bhagavad-gItA-parva/meta/abhinavagupta-gItArtha-sangrahaH/0/boudon_torzsok/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/mahAbhAratam/vyAsaH/shlokashaH/bhagavad-gItA-parva/meta/abhinavagupta-gItArtha-sangrahaH/0/boudon_torzsok/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;J Indian Philos&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;DOI 10.1007/s10781-017-9335-1&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Abhinavagupta on the Kashmirian Gītā&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Announcement of the First Critical Edition of the Gītārthasaṃgraha, with the Reconstruction of the Text of the Kashmirian Gītā as Abhinavagupta Probably Read It and a French Translation of Both Texts&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Lyne Bansat-Boudon1 · Judit Törzsök2&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;© Springer Science+Business Media B.V. 2017&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This paper announces the first critical edition of Abhinavagupta’s commentary (entitled Gītārthasaṃgraha) on the Bhagavadgītā in its Kashmirian recension, based on one Kashmirian Devana¯garı¯ and seven Sá¯rada¯ manuscripts in addition to two existing non-critical editions. The volume will also include a new edition of the Kashmirian recension of the Bhagavadgītā and a full French translation. After a short presentation of Abhinavagupta’s commentary and a discussion of previous work on the subject, the manuscripts used are listed and briefly described. The question and importance of the Kashmirian recension of the Bhagavadgītā and problems of its edition are discussed in detail, with several textual examples. In order to give a sample of the Gītārthasaṃgraha’s contents, some of Abhinavagupta’s remarkable interpretations are also highlighted, in particular tantric or esoteric ones. An Appendix deals with the closely related question of Bha¯skara the Veda¯ntin, his date, his provenance and the Gītā recension he probably used for his commentary.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Boudon Torzsok alt</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/mahAbhAratam/vyAsaH/shlokashaH/bhagavad-gItA-parva/meta/abhinavagupta-gItArtha-sangrahaH/0/boudon_torzsok_alt/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/mahAbhAratam/vyAsaH/shlokashaH/bhagavad-gItA-parva/meta/abhinavagupta-gItArtha-sangrahaH/0/boudon_torzsok_alt/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;obvious-errors-the-other-one-from-the-bori-see-b-below-although-it-contains-fewer-minor-mistakes-often-transmits-corrupt-or-secondary-readings-eg-akṣāder-for-kṣader-in-11-pāṇḍavaḥ-for-pāṇḍavāḥ-in-11-seṣabuddya-for-viseṣabuddhyā-in-135-if-the-readings-of-these-two-manuscripts-had-been-included-in-the-edition-it-would-have-resulted-in-an-inflated-apparatus-which-is-already-rather-voluminous-as-it-stands-and-would-have-slowed-down-the-collation-procedure-considerably-the-variants-in-these-two-mss-for-the-introductory-verse-and-the-first-chapter-shall-be-made-available-in-an-appendix-which-will-show-that-sometimes-both-manuscripts-transmit-the-same-secondary-reading-furthermore-their-readings-also-often-agree-with-those-of-pansîkars-edition-which-suggests-that-the-manuscripts-used-in-pansîkars-edition-may-also-belong-to-this-relatively-corrupt-subgroup-in-fact-our-b-and-pansîkars-edition-agree-so-often-that-initially-we-thought-that-pansîkar-used-b-but-this-hypothesis-is-contradicted-by-some-disagreements-of-variants-it-must-also-be-pointed-out-that-this-b-is-identical-with-manuscript-b-of-the-tirupati-edition-published-by-sankaranarayanan-one-could-therefore-also-consult-that-edition-to-see-what-b-reads-however-comparing-our-collation-of-the-first-chapter-with-that-of-sankaranarayanans-edition-it-seems-that-the-latter-omits-to-report-a-large-number-of-small-variants-found-in-b-thus-it-cannot-be-taken-to-represent-b-faithfully-our-list-of-mss-with-the-abbreviations-used-is-as-follows2&#34;&gt;J Indian Philos&#xA;DOI 10.1007/s10781-017-9335-1&#xA;Abhinavagupta on the Kashmirian Gītā&#xA;Announcement of the First Critical Edition of the Gītārthasamgraha, with the Reconstruction of the Text of the Kashmirian Gītā as Abhinavagupta Probably Read It and a French Translation of Both Texts&#xA;Lyne Bansat-Boudon&amp;rsquo; Judit Törzsök2&#xA;Springer Science+Business Media B.V. 2017&#xA;CrossMark&#xA;Abstract This paper announces the first critical edition of Abhinavagupta&amp;rsquo;s commentary (entitled Gitärthasamgraha) on the Bhagavadgītā in its Kashmirian recension, based on one Kashmirian Devanagarī and seven Saradā manuscripts in addition to two existing non-critical editions. The volume will also include a new edition of the Kashmirian recension of the Bhagavadgītā and a full French translation. After a short presentation of Abhinavagupta&amp;rsquo;s commentary and a discussion of previous work on the subject, the manuscripts used are listed and briefly described. The question and importance of the Kashmirian recension of the Bhagavadgītā and problems of its edition are discussed in detail, with several textual examples. In order to give a sample of the Gitärthasamgraha&amp;rsquo;s contents, some of Abhinavagupta&amp;rsquo;s remarkable interpretations are also highlighted, in particular tantric or esoteric ones. An Appendix deals with the closely related question of Bhaskara the Vedāntin, his date, his provenance and the Gītā recension he probably used for his commentary.&#xA;.&#xA;Keywords Abhinavagupta Kashmirian recension Bhagavadgītā · Gitārthasamgraha Saivism Bhaskara Rāmakaṇṭha Critical edition&#xA;1&#xA;2&#xA;Judit Törzsök&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;mailto:torzsokjudit@hotmail.com&#34;&gt;torzsokjudit@hotmail.com&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;Lyne Bansat-Boudon&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;mailto:lyne.bansat-boudon@ephe.sorbonne.fr&#34;&gt;lyne.bansat-boudon@ephe.sorbonne.fr&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;Section des Sciences religieuses, École pratique des hautes études, Les Patios Saint-Jacques, 4-14 rue Ferrus, 75014 Paris, France&#xA;Dpt. Langues et cultures antiques, Université Charles-de-Gaulle Lille III, Domaine Universitaire du Pont de Bois, BP 60149, 59653 Villeneuve d&amp;rsquo;Ascq Cedex, France&#xA;Published online: 02 November 2017&#xA;Springer&#xA;L. Bansat-Boudon, J. Törzsök&#xA;Introduction&#xA;This paper announces the first critical edition of Abhinavagupta&amp;rsquo;s commentary on the Bhagavadgītā entitled &amp;lsquo;The Summary of the Meaning of the Gītā (Gītārthasamgraha, henceforth GAS), which will be accompanied by a French translation based on the critically edited text. This commentary is probably an early work of the young Abhinavagupta (Sanderson 2007, pp. 359-60), and as the title shows, it is a short commentary (samgraha), sometimes glossing only a few expressions in the verses and sometimes not commenting on them at all. It is nevertheless a unique work in several respects.&#xA;First, it gives us a Saiva interpretation of a fundamentally Vaiṣṇava work and therefore reveals the ways in which Śaivas, or at least certain Śaivas, appropriated this text. It thus shows us how much so-called &amp;lsquo;sectarian boundaries&amp;rsquo; within the Hindu fold were not very rigidly understood, at least not in Abhinavagupta&amp;rsquo;s Kashmir.&#xA;Second, given Abhinavagupta&amp;rsquo;s tantric background, his commentary also provides us with numerous instances in which he gives particularly esoteric interpretations of some passages. He often introduces such interpretations by saying that he now gives the meaning of the verse according to &amp;lsquo;secret teachings&amp;rsquo; (rahasya, rahasyopadeśa), which mostly introduces esoteric Krama exegesis (Sanderson 2007, pp. 357ff.). These passages reveal that the text of the Gītā, which was certainly not meant to be particularly esoteric in the first place, was nevertheless the object of esoteric exegesis, which could have been a means for certain esoteric schools to connect with more mundane (laukika) forms of religion. This remains hypothetical of course, but the existence of such highly speculative understanding of the Gītā, whether it circulated among members of esoteric schools3 or was Abhinavagupta&amp;rsquo;s own personal interpretation, is itself remarkable.&#xA;Third, Abhinavagupta&amp;rsquo;s commentary provides us with what is one of the earliest testimonies of the Kashmirian recension of the Bhagavadgītā. Even if he does not comment on every verse or every single word, it is clear that he used what we can call the Kashmirian recension, which diverges from the so-called Vulgate and from&#xA;1 See for instance his fifth mangala verse (udyamo me tadgūḍhārthaprakāśakaḥ) and his commentary on 3.11, 3.48, and 11.18, also cited in Sanderson (2007, pp. 357ff.).&#xA;2 See e.g. the often-cited passage saying that even women, vaisyas and sūdras can have access to it and obtain final release: mām hi pārtha vyapāśritya ye &amp;lsquo;pi syuḥ papayonayaḥ | striyo vaisyās tathā sūdrās te &amp;lsquo;pi yanti parām gatim | 9.32.&#xA;3 Abhinavagupta himself states in his invocation (verse 6) that he follows Bhaṭṭenduraja&amp;rsquo;s tradition of interpretation, to which he adds his own thoughts (bhaṭṭendurājād ämnaya vivicya ca ciram dhiya). This suggests that he bases his interpretation on an existing (perhaps esoteric) tradition, but he does not refrain from providing his own personal understanding either (see e.g. his commentary on 3.11). Let us note that Vasugupta, founder of the Spanda school and belonging to the same guruparampara as Bhaṭṭendurāja, is also known to have written a commentary on the Gītā, called the Vasavi Ṭīkā (now lost); see J.C. Chatterji (1914, p. 37), Schrader (1935, p. 354, n. 20), Chintamani (1941, pp. xxi and xxxviii).&#xA;4 In addition to Ramakantḥa&amp;rsquo;s (950-1000) and, probably, Bhaskara&amp;rsquo;s (9th c.?) works, the Sarvatobhadra and the Bhagavadāśayānusaraṇa respectively. For a more detailed discussion of these and the question of the Kashmirian recension, see below &amp;lsquo;The Kashmirian Gītā and Its Relation to the Vulgate&amp;rsquo; and our Appendix.&#xA;Springer&#xA;Abhinavagupta on the Kashmirian Gītā&#xA;5&#xA;the critical edition of the epic (Sukthankar et al.) in many respects. The evaluation of the differences is not at all straightforward. For the moment, we can only affirm that the majority of variants seem to show that the Kashmirian recension often retains the primary reading, but there are ambiguous cases and several additional verses in the Kashmirian Gītā, which may point to it being secondary, at least in some passages, as pointed out below.&#xA;No matter how we evaluate the relationship of the Gītā recensions, it is certainly an important task for us to provide the text of the Gītā as Abhinavagupta probably read it. Because of the concise nature of the commentary, it is often impossible to know what Abhinavagupta read exactly. We have nevertheless attempted to provide a full reconstruction of the Kashmirian Gītā, wherever possible on the basis of Abhinavagupta&amp;rsquo;s commentary, and wherever his commentary could not help, on the basis of manuscripts containing his mula and other Kashmirian testimonies.&amp;quot;&#xA;Previous Work and Our Task&#xA;We know of three previous editions of the Gītārthasamgraha, none of which is a critical one for several reasons. None of them has attempted to consult all available sources, no appropriate description of the manuscripts is given and editorial policies are not explained. Moreover, having consulted some MSS used by these editors and looking at their apparatus, it is also obvious that not all variant readings are reported. In spite of these common drawbacks of traditional Indian editions, one of them (Pandit Lakshman Joo&amp;rsquo;s) is an outstanding contribution.&#xA;The first edition of the Gītārthasamgraha was published in Bombay by the Nirnaya Sagar Press in 1912, edited by Wâsudev Laxman Shâstrî Pansîkar (henceforth called the Pansîkar edition). In this thick volume, several other commentaries on the Gītā are also included, along with the text of the Gītā printed on top of each page. From this format, it is obvious that the editor did not intend to reproduce the variations in the text of the mula as read by the different commentators. Indeed, Abhinavagupta&amp;rsquo;s commentary very often does not correspond to what is printed as the mūla, which basically agrees with the Vulgate.&#xA;This is, however, not the most serious problem. In many cases, Abhinavagupta&amp;rsquo;s text does not yield any sense at all as printed, which renders this edition of his&#xA;8&#xA;5&#xA;For a discussion of the possible definitions of the Vulgate, see below &amp;lsquo;The Kashmirian Gītā and Its Relation to the Vulgate.&amp;rsquo;&#xA;6 As explained below, these include most importantly Ramakaṇṭha&amp;rsquo;s and Bhaskara&amp;rsquo;s commentaries as well as Kashmirian citations of the Gītā. Summaries such as Kṣemendra&amp;rsquo;s Bhāratamañjarī are also helpful on some occasions.&#xA;7 Usually only one or two variants are reported on each page, often none at all, which in itself shows that only select variants have been included.&#xA;8 This is obvious from the very beginning, for Abhinavagupta reads and comments sarvakṣatrasamāgame in the first verse instead of the well-known samaveta yuyutsavaḥ. Schrader (1930, p. 1) already pointed out this inconsistency.&#xA;Springer&#xA;L. Bansat-Boudon, J. Törzsök&#xA;commentary and any translation based on it of limited use.&amp;quot; The editor states that he used a corrupt (lit. &amp;rsquo;not too accurate,&amp;rsquo; nātiśuddha) MS allegedly from Kashmir10 and another one, said to be generally correct (prayaḥ śuddham), which seems to be close to, but not necessarily identical with, our MS B. Because the edited text is extremely corrupt, we have decided not to report any variant of this edition.&#xA;11&#xA;The second edition came out in 1933, in Shrinagar, produced by the young Swami Lakshman Joo, under the name of Pandit Lakshman Raina. He used several Śārada MSS, without describing them in detail. 12 From the notes on variant readings (using four sigla: Ka Kha Ga and Gha), it can be inferred that he must have used more than the three main MSS he claims to in his introduction, but no matter how many MSS he used, he reports variants very sporadically. Moreover, he introduces his own emendations and conjectures without signalling them as such. Although most of these conjectures are rather ingenious, they mostly prove to be unjustified when looking at the manuscript evidence at our disposal.13 It is the edition of a learned pandit, who sometimes interferes with the text according to his personal taste. This is, nevertheless, the best available edition by far and was used, without any acknowledgement, by B. Marjanovic in his translation (2002).&#xA;9 The editor himself remarks the incoherence of the text in a footnote at 2.48: upalabdhobhayādarśapustakayor apīyam vyākhyā sambaddhatraiva drsyate. [This incoherent/unconnected commentary is seen right here in both manuscripts we have obtained.&amp;rsquo;] Arvind Sharma&amp;rsquo;s English translation (1983), which is unfortunately based on Pansîkar&amp;rsquo;s edition, is problematic in several places, although he occasionally consults Kashmirian variants given in the critical edition of the Gītā. For instance in 1.1 Sharma does not seem to notice that Abhinavagupta&amp;rsquo;s mūla is different from Pansîkar&amp;rsquo;s text, the former reading sarvakṣatra(with all the Kashmirian sources), the latter sarvakṣetra(with the Vulgate). Therefore, Sharma fails to translate the explanation of kṣatra derived from the root kṣadaccording to Abhinavagupta&amp;rsquo;s commentary. Similarly, it is unclear whether Gnoli&amp;rsquo;s Italian translation (1976) is based on Pansîkar&amp;rsquo;s or Lakshman Joo&amp;rsquo;s text of the Gītā, although his translation of the GAS is certainly based on Lakshman Joo&amp;rsquo;s edition. Nevertheless, it is possible that Gnoli follows Pansîkar, at least occasionally, since he seems to elude the difficulty already noticed about Sharma&amp;rsquo;s translation of GAS ad 1.1 for instance; Gnoli also appears to translate sarvakṣetrainstead of sarvakṣatra-, which is the variant supported by our MSS and by the semantic analysis given by Abhinavagupta.&#xA;10 This MS was provided by Pandit Kedāranāth, Durgāprasad&amp;rsquo;s son. It is possible that this MS is the same as our S5 in Sarada script, found in the BORI and also used in the Tirupati edition by Sankaranarayanan (discussed below), but the editor does not provide any information about the script.&#xA;11 It is said to come from Deccan College, Pune. Since variants are rarely reported in the Pansîkar edition, we cannot be certain that our MS B in Devanagarī (from the BORI) is identical with this. See also Schrader (1930, p. 4).&#xA;12 He states to have used three Śārada MSS, but also to have made a copy of the first one &amp;lsquo;with the help of many other manuscript copies&amp;rsquo;, which suggests that his so-called first MS (= Ka?) is the result of conflating several ones.&#xA;13 See for instance his conjectural reading samasirṣakatayā for samatayā in the avataraṇikā to 1.1, which is not supported by any evidence in the MSS at our disposal; or the reading anabhāvāt (anabhāva as a word being a hapax) for abhāvāt in 2.16, again without any manuscript support. The latter conjecture is probably due to the omission of a previous negation in his edition.&#xA;14 The Sanskrit text given in this translation agrees with Lakshman Joo&amp;rsquo;s edition, with the addition of typographic errors, which, surprisingly, often agree with those of the e-text (dated 2011) of the Muktabodha Indological Research Institute, also based on Lakshman Joo&amp;rsquo;s edition. See e.g., in mangala 2, mādhānyataḥ for pradhānyataḥ; in mangala 3, ākānkṣya for ākānkṣayā and prathiḥ for prathitaḥ; GAS ad 1.1: sarvakṣetrāṇām for sarvakṣatrāṇām; BhG 1.9, where he adds (agreeing with the Muktabodha e-text) a &amp;rsquo;nāsti&amp;rsquo; in the second hemistich, which produces faulty metre; BhG 1.26, where he reads pitṛn atha instead of pitṛn atha; BhG 18.62, where he reads tatprasādāt, which is the text of the Vulgate,&#xA;Springer&#xA;Abhinavagupta on the Kashmirian Gītā&#xA;16&#xA;17&#xA;Another great merit of Lakshman Joo&amp;rsquo;s edition is that he includes the text of the Gītā as probably read by Abhinavagupta.&amp;quot; He does not say so, but his readings often (though not always) seem to agree with the Kashmirian recension of the Gītā, and it certainly corresponds on the whole to what Abhinavagupta probably read. Indeed, so much so that occasionally Lakshman Joo even changes the text of the Gītā in accordance with what he thinks Abhinavagupta had in front of him.&amp;quot; Unfortunately, Lakshman Joo is silent on how he constitutes the text of the Gītā, which manuscripts he used for it and what editorial principles he adopted. This, however, did not deter the editors of the Mahabharata from using this edition of the Gītā as if it were a manuscript, saying that &amp;rsquo;the printed text can reasonably be taken to represent Raina&amp;rsquo;s best MS&amp;rsquo; (Belvalkar 1947, p. lvii). Therefore, the siglum S3 in the Gītā as printed in the critical edition of the Mahābhārata does not represent a manuscript, but Lakshman Joo&amp;rsquo;s text, which is a methodological problem. Moreover, the siglum Cg represents exactly the same text, for it is meant to stand for what Abhinavagupta read according to Lakshman Joo&amp;rsquo;s edition.19&#xA;18&#xA;Although it is evident from the small number of variants in the footnotes that Lakshman Joo did not report all the variants, he did so on a number of occasions, especially when the reading was somewhat problematic.20 Some of these variants are helpful for us in establishing the reading, therefore we have decided to report all&#xA;Footnote 14 continued&#xA;whereas the GAS comments on matprasādāt, with all the philosophical implications of that variant; GAS ad 18.62: hiranapotakāḥ (for harinapotakāḥ) and so on. See also kṣetrajñahaḥ (obviously a barbarism) in his translation of GAS ad 13.3, which is but what he must have heard or grasped of his master&amp;rsquo;s pronunciation of the visarga in kṣetrajñaḥ. This last error shows that Marjanovic must have based his translation on his notes reproducing his master&amp;rsquo;s (Prof. Shri Narayana Mishra&amp;rsquo;s) oral teaching. Another proof of this is his translation of pratiṣṭhā in GAS ad 14.27, which he translates as &amp;lsquo;seed&amp;rsquo; instead of &amp;lsquo;seat&amp;rsquo; (in aham eva hi brahmaṇaḥ pratiṣṭhā), a result of having misheard his master.&#xA;15 He reports variants of Ka, Ga and Gha for the text of the Gītā (e.g. p. 32 Ka, p. 33 Ga and once p. 111 Gha), which means that he had at least three manuscripts to constitute the mula.&#xA;16 The question of what can be called the Kashmirian recension of the Gītā is discussed below &amp;lsquo;The Kashmirian Gītā and Its Relation to the Vulgate.&amp;rsquo;&#xA;17 This results in a completely unsupported reading of muḍhācāraḥ for mithyācāraḥ in 3.6d. Here, Abhinavagupta probably summarizes the verse by contracting two adjectives of the Gītā, vimūḍhātmā and mithyācāraḥ, into one mūḍhācāraḥ (the reading of all our MSS). Lakshman Joo, however, seems to assume that Abhinavagupta must have read mūḍhācāraḥ in the text of the Gītā itself, and replaces the received reading of mithyācāraḥ (read by all the Kashmirian sources as well as the Vulgate) by mūḍhācāraḥ in the text of the mula. Later on, the commentary on verse 12 cites this compound once more, and all MSS read mithyācāraḥ in the commentary. This is changed again into mūḍhācāraḥ by Lakshman Joo, this time to be consistent with his previous conjecture. We are grateful to Yuko Yokochi who contributed to solving this problem.&#xA;18 Another error of method&amp;rsquo; in Belvalkar&amp;rsquo;s treatment of the Gītā recensions is pointed out by van Buitenen (1965, p. 103); for Belvalkar simply uses T.R. Chintamani&amp;rsquo;s select extracts to report Bhaskara&amp;rsquo;s readings. For these problems, see below &amp;lsquo;The Kashmirian Gītā and Its Relation to the Vulgate.&amp;rsquo;&#xA;19 This results in such readings in the apparatus of the critical edition as mūḍhācāraḥ for mithyācāraḥ in 3.6d (see note 17), which is in fact Lakshman Joo&amp;rsquo;s conjecture, but appears as supported by S3 and Cg in the critical edition.&#xA;20 At least this is our impression, see e.g. in the commentary on 3.15, p. 36, where he rejects the reading of all his available MSS (probably considering a citation from Manu an interpolation); or in the mula at 3.39b, in which he rejects his MS Ga (indriyeșu ha), although this is what Abhinavagupta seems to read (utpattisamaye &amp;rsquo;lakṣya indriyeṣu), and adopts indriyaiḥ saha of the Vulgate (agreeing with our S1 and S2).&#xA;Springer&#xA;L. Bansat-Boudon, J. Törzsök&#xA;the variants found in Lakshman Joo&amp;rsquo;s edition, in addition to report of course the readings Lakshman Joo adopted, both for the commentary and for the Gītā.&#xA;The third edition was published in 1985, in Tirupati, by Sankaranarayanan at the Sri Venkateswara University. In addition to Lakshman Joo&amp;rsquo;s edition, the editor also uses a Sārada manuscript (the same as our S5) and a rather corrupt Devanagarī one (our B), both from Pune. As we shall see, the additional manuscript evidence used here consists of two sources that are certainly not among the most useful ones. But more importantly, this edition does not question most of Lakshman Joo&amp;rsquo;s unmarked conjectures and reproduces them often without any sign to show that they are actually conjectures. In fact, the text of the commentary as given by Sankaranarayanan deviates very rarely from Lakshman Joo&amp;rsquo;s edition, except for the fact that pratīkas are used particularly generously. This overuse of the pratīkas is not based on manuscript evidence, but is a personal decision of the editor, &amp;lsquo;for the sake of convenience&amp;rsquo; (p. liii). Similarly to Lakshman Joo, Sankaranarayanan also seems to interfere with the text of the Gītā when he deems it necessary, without any support from the manuscripts.22 Because of the heavy reliance of this edition on Lakshman Joo&amp;rsquo;s, and because we have consulted the MSS used in it ourselves, we have decided not to include the variants of this edition, unless they deviate from Lakshman Joo&amp;rsquo;s.2&#xA;From the description of the available editions, the need for a critical edition seems to be rather obvious. We have thus collected all manuscript sources we were aware of, out of which the most important ones seem to be the Saradā manuscripts.&#xA;Manuscript Sources of the Edition&#xA;23&#xA;We have identified altogether ten manuscripts containing the Gītārthasamgraha, out of which five (S1, S2, S6, S7 and J) also contain the text of the Bhagavadgītā. All the ten manuscripts consulted are on paper, seven of them are written in Śāradā characters (under the siglum S) and three in Devanagarī. Out of these ten manuscripts, only eight have been fully collated and used to constitute the text. This was done because after collating the introductory verse and the first chapter, it turned out that two of the Devanagarī manuscripts are not particularly useful: one of them (from Jammu, see J2 below) is very corrupt and transmits a large number of&#xA;21 See e.g. at avataraṇikā to 1.1 cited above (accepting Lakshman Joo&amp;rsquo;s samaśīrṣakatayā for samatayā, or rather, correcting it to [or misprinting it as?] samaśīrṣataya); see also in the commentary on 3.12 printing mudhācāraḥ following Lakshman Joo rather than the MSS&amp;rsquo; mithyācāraḥ. Neither of these is identified as a conjecture.&#xA;22 Sankaranarayanan had no additional evidence for establishing the text of the Gītā, therefore wherever his text reads differently, it is because of his (often silently made) conjectural emendations. They are sometimes very little supported (e.g. in 3.3a conjecturing puraikoktā for purā proktā without any MS evidence), but sometimes appear to be justified on the basis of Abhinavagupta&amp;rsquo;s text (such as indriyeṣu ha in 3.39b cited in note 20).&#xA;23 It does happen occasionally that the editor provides a very good conjecture or insight. At 3.39b cited above (note 20), indriyeșu ha is what Abhinavagupta seems to read, but Lakshman Joo adopts the Vulgate&amp;rsquo;s indriyaiḥ saha for some unaccountable reason. Sankaranarayanan&amp;rsquo;s edition adopts, rightly, indriyeșu ha (which is also the reading of Lakshman Joo&amp;rsquo;s MS Ga), without, however, noting whether it is a conjecture or MS reading.&#xA;Springer&#xA;Abhinavagupta on the Kashmirian Gītā&#xA;obvious errors; the other one (from the BORI, see B below), although it contains fewer minor mistakes, often transmits corrupt or secondary readings (e.g. akṣāder for kṣader in 1.1, pāṇḍavaḥ for pāṇḍavāḥ in 1.1, seṣabuddya for viseṣabuddhyā in 1.35). If the readings of these two manuscripts had been included in the edition, it would have resulted in an inflated apparatus, which is already rather voluminous as it stands, and would have slowed down the collation procedure considerably. The variants in these two MSS for the introductory verse and the first chapter shall be made available in an appendix, which will show that sometimes both manuscripts transmit the same secondary reading. Furthermore, their readings also often agree with those of Pansîkar&amp;rsquo;s edition, which suggests that the manuscripts used in Pansîkar&amp;rsquo;s edition may also belong to this relatively corrupt subgroup. In fact our B and Pansîkar&amp;rsquo;s edition agree so often that initially we thought that Pansîkar used B, but this hypothesis is contradicted by some disagreements of variants. It must also be pointed out that this B is identical with manuscript B of the Tirupati edition published by Sankaranarayanan; one could therefore also consult that edition to see what B reads. However, comparing our collation of the first chapter with that of Sankaranarayanan&amp;rsquo;s edition, it seems that the latter omits to report a large number of small variants found in B, thus, it cannot be taken to represent B faithfully. Our list of MSS with the abbreviations used is as follows:2&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;h1 id=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;.24&#xA;S1 Śārada on paper, Banaras Hindu University acc. no. C 42 (S. no. 3G/3425). 88 folios. Very clear and neat handwriting. Marginal additions by a second hand. Small vertical lines to separate words and avagraha signs to mark various elisions of the a are added in a less thick ink and probably by a second hand (these marks are not reported). Also contains the text of the Gītā, usually according to the Vulgate. A lot of insertions and glosses are seen in the margins, both in the original hand and in a second hand, whose akṣaras are thinner and whose writing is less regular. No date, but the writing was commissioned by a śaiva devotee called Nārāyaṇa. Catalogued in Tripathi (1971, pp. 334-5).&#xA;S2&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;h1 id=&#34;s3&#34;&gt;Śārada on paper, Banaras Hindu University acc. no. C 1016 (S. no. 3G/3446). 79 folios. Also contains the text of the Gītā. The text of the Gītā, when it runs through several verses, is usually indented. This Gītā follows mainly the Vulgate, but occasionally it is the only MS that has the good Kashmirian Gītā reading (in e.g. 1.10). Dated 1906-7 AD. Catalogued in Tripathi (1971, pp. 336–7).&#xA;S3&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Śārada on paper, Banaras Hindu University acc. no. C 1099 (S. no. 3G/3297). 34 folios. Contains only the commentary. Dated samvat 82. Catalogued in Tripāṭhī (1971, pp. 332-3).&#xA;S4 = Sārada on paper, Banaras Hindu University acc. no. C 3981. (S. no. 3G/3444) 117 folios, bound as a book. Very clear and neat hand, but several small errors. Contains only the commentary. The MS starts with other texts, such as a certain Bhuvanamālinīkalpavivaraṇa. Lots of marginalia and sometimes very idiosyncratic readings (in e.g. the commentary on 1.1 aparihartavyāni for apahartavyāni). Ends&#xA;24&#xA;Note that we use digital photos for the collation of these MSS.&#xA;Springer&#xA;L. Bansat-Boudon, J. Törzsök&#xA;abruptly in the middle of the Stavacintamani with commentary, page 126 of KSTS ed. Not dated. Catalogued in Tripathi (1971, pp. 336-7).&#xA;S5 = Śārada, Bhandarkar Oriental Research Institute, 163/1883-84. (New no. 1517.) The same as MS S in Sankaranarayanan&amp;rsquo;s Tirupati edition. Not catalogued. For a detailed description, see Sankaranarayanan (1985 part 1, pp. xlix ff.). Contains only the commentary. Several marginal glosses. No date. Many small errors.&#xA;S6=Śārada, Shrinagar, Oriental Research Library, n. 2308. Bound as a book. Large, thickly written pages. Contains only the commentary with pratīkas till verse 2.11. Verse 2.11, which is missing in the Vulgate, is found in S6, which has its first citation of the Gītā at this point including the preceding speaker indication. It then omits the subsequent verses till 14 and gives the full text of the Gītā from verse 15 onwards. Dated 1896-7. Written by a certain Kṛṣṇadāsa.&#xA;S7 = Śārada, Shrinagar, Oriental Research Library, no. 1612. This manuscript also contains extracts from Rāmakaṇṭha&amp;rsquo;s commentary on the Gītā. Includes the text of the Gītā. The Gītā is written in larger characters on each page with a wide margin, and extracts from the commentaries are copied in the margins at the appropriate places. There are numerous omissions in Abhinavagupta&amp;rsquo;s commentary, the scribe (or a scribe somewhere in the transmission) perhaps made a deliberate choice of copying only certain passages. Given the format, it seems that first the text of the Gītā was written in full, and then the commentaries were added to it, i.e. this Gītā may have come from outside the transmission of the commentary. Whatever the case may be, this Gītā seems to represent the Kashmirian recension and, in addition to being conform to Abhinavagupta&amp;rsquo;s commentary, it also agrees mostly with Ramakantha&amp;rsquo;s and Bhaskara&amp;rsquo;s readings and Schrader&amp;rsquo;s edition of the Kashmirian Gītā. Incomplete, stops at 16.11c, no date.&#xA;J = Jammu, Shri Ranbir Sanskrit Research Library Jammu Tawi, N. 209. 64 folios. Devanagari. Contains the text of the Gītā. A lot of obvious mistakes, but often seems to retain original readings going with the Śārada MSS. Seems to transmit the Kashmirian recension of the Gītā on the whole. No date. Catalogued in Stein (1894, p. 195) as Bhagavadgītārthasamgraha under no. 930, said to be written in modern Kashmirian writing (navīnā kāśmīrikī lipiḥ).&#xA;Manuscripts consulted but not collated for the edition:&#xA;J2 = Jammu, Shri Ranbir Sanskrit Research Library Jammu Tawi, N. 250. J2 Devanagari. Contains only the commentary. Often agrees with B, both having secondary readings. Incomplete. Stops at commentary on 18.67. No date.&#xA;B = Bhandarkar Oriental Research Institute MS no. 422/1875-76 (new no. 28), in Devanagari. Same as MS B in Sankaranarayanan&amp;rsquo;s 1985 edition described in part 1, pp. xlix ff. Contains only the commentary. With many secondary readings, often agreeing also with J2. Dated 1895.&#xA;Springer&#xA;Abhinavagupta on the Kashmirian Gītā&#xA;The Kashmirian Gītā and Its Relation to the Vulgate&#xA;While preparing the edition of the commentary, it became increasingly apparent that a new edition of the mūla, i.e. the Kashmirian Gītā, was inevitable. Five of our manuscripts also include the text of the Gītā, but in spite of this evidence, it is sometimes very difficult to decide what Abhinavagupta could have read, given the concise nature of the commentary and because the Kashmirian manuscripts also seem to have been influenced by the Vulgate.25 We therefore realized that external sources also needed to be consulted to reproduce Abhinavagupta&amp;rsquo;s Kashmirian Gītā, which led us to consider various questions concerning the Kashmirian recension and its status as compared to the Vulgate.&#xA;The textual reconstruction of the Gītā should certainly start with that of the Mahābhārata, since, no matter how we try to establish the different layers of composition of the epic, the Gītā is part of it. For a start, a definition of what the Vulgate consists of should be found. Now, the Vulgate of the epic itself is considered, by scholarly consensus, to be identical with the Poona edition by Kinjawadekar (1929-1936), which includes Nilakantha&amp;rsquo;s commentary. One could therefore identify the Vulgate of the Bhagavadgītā with what is printed in the Poona edition, which is what Belvalkar (1941, p. 18, note 3) and Biardeau (2002 I, pp. 1820) do.&#xA;26&#xA;Next to this edition, however, we also have the text of the Gītā that Śankara (and his school, as emphasized by Schrader 1935, p. 148) comments upon. Because of Sankara&amp;rsquo;s importance in Indian thought, and because he is perhaps the earliest known commentator of the text,27 his mula (Apațe 1936; Gokhale 1950) has come to be seen as the Gītā by several scholars, such as Schrader (1930, p. 18, 1935, p. 148, 1934, p. 352), T.R. Chintamani (1941, p. xx), van Buitenen (1965, p. 104) and Kato (2014, p. 1146). Let us note that Śankara does not comment on the first 57 stanzas, which includes the entire first chapter. It is interesting to observe in this context that Tadpatrikar in his edition of Ramakantha&amp;rsquo;s commentary on the Kashmirian Gītā gives Sankara&amp;rsquo;s variants for comparison (śānkarapāṭhaḥ) at each&#xA;28&#xA;25 The strong influence of the Vulgate even on Kashmirian sources was already pointed out by Schrader (1930, p. 2). Belvalkar (1945) expressed doubts about the existence of a Kashmirian recension and the rather overpowering influence of the Vulgate, maintaining that in fact no real Kashmirian recension had ever existed. We can prove at least part of Schrader&amp;rsquo;s argument, namely that variants from the Vulgate influenced the copyists: for when we consulted and checked the e-text of Lakshman Joo&amp;rsquo;s edition prepared at the Muktabodha Institute, it turned out that the copyist of the e-text replaced several times the Kashmirian readings of Lakshman Joo&amp;rsquo;s edition with those of the Vulgate. Thus, the overpowering influence of the Vulgate can be felt even to this day. E.g. in 2.1c the e-text reads viṣīdantam (Vulgate) for sīdamānam (Kashmirian/Lakshman Joo); 2.12 [= 2.11 Vulgate] reads asocyan anvaśocas tvam (Vulgate) for Lakshman Joo&amp;rsquo;s Kashmirian asocyan anusocams tvam; 2.55 [= 2.53 Vulgate] reads yadā sthāsyati niścalā (Vulgate) for yadā sthāsyati niścitā (Kashmirian/Lakshman Joo).&#xA;26&#xA;We take Sankara to be the author of the Gītā commentary attributed to him, although the authenticity of this text has been questioned several times (see e.g. Sarma 1933a, Chintamani 1941, p. xxiv, Mayeda 1965).&#xA;27 This depends on the identification and date of Bhāskara, who may have been Sankara&amp;rsquo;s immediate successor or even his contemporary. For a discussion, see the Appendix.&#xA;28 This implies that one cannot speak of the Vulgate for this chapter before Rāmānuja (11th-12th c.), as van Buitenen (1965, p. 103) observes. For more on this question, see Bansat-Boudon (2015, p. 93).&#xA;Springer&#xA;L. Bansat-Boudon, J. Törzsök&#xA;verse, below the Kashmirian reading. He thus also appears to consider Śankara&amp;rsquo;s text the Vulgate.&#xA;What may be called the third Vulgate was edited as part of the critical edition of the Mahabharata and reprinted in 1945 separately by Belvalkar. This text corresponds mostly to Sankara&amp;rsquo;s text except for 14 minor variants and has been considered the Vulgate by some scholars such as Gnoli (1976, pp. 39-40) and even, somewhat surprisingly, by van Buitenen in his translation of the Gītā, published in 1981.29 Since this text has become regarded as the received text of the Gītā, we refer to this edition in our apparatus. Let us remark here, nevertheless, that in this part of the Mahābhārata, the editors did not maintain their general principle of following the Kashmirian recension on the whole. 30 As has been suggested,31 this is perhaps due to the importance of Sankara and his version of the Gītā, which was too wellknown to replace, even if Belvalkar seems to argue otherwise.32 Whatever the reasons were for this choice, here we have, by and large, Śankara&amp;rsquo;s Gītā again.&#xA;Next to these three, which are slightly different versions of what we may call the Vulgate of the Gītā, the existence of a distinct Kashmirian recension was noticed early on.33 Otto Schrader&amp;rsquo;s study (Schrader 1930) of the Kashmirian recension is a very valuable source for us, for he notes all the variants compared to the Vulgate, on the basis of a birch-bark manuscript of Sarada characters (dated 1750) and on the basis of what he manages to reconstruct as the Kashmirian readings from Rāmakantha&amp;rsquo;s and Abhinavagupta&amp;rsquo;s commentaries.34 Schrader did remark that the Kashmirian readings appeared to be primary at several places.35 His opinion started a heated debate36 that has flared up even recently, but contrarily to the original debate, without any actual philological arguments and purely on a moral-political basis.3&#xA;37&#xA;29 See van Buitenen (1981, p. xii): &amp;lsquo;The text reproduced is that presented by S.K. Belvalkar as part of the critical edition of the Mahabharata [&amp;hellip;]. For the Gītā itself this is virtually the vulgate.&amp;rsquo; It is surprising that van Buitenen bases his translation on the Vulgate after showing the numerous problems it contains in his paper of 1965. See below.&#xA;30 See van Buitenen (1965, p. 101): &amp;lsquo;In the critical edition of the Bhagavadgītā the remarkable fact emerges that, while the MSS. of the Saradā Kashmir tradition are generally the most authoritative for the earliest text of the epic, including the Bhismaparvan where the Gītā is found, nevertheless they are found to be late and secondary as far as the text of the Gītā is concerned.&amp;rsquo;&#xA;31 This is not explicitly stated by van Buitenen, who writes (1965, p. 102): &amp;lsquo;The earliest testimony concerning the Gītā is that of Sankara, and the Gītā text adopted by the Editor is really Sankara&amp;rsquo;s text with but 14 highly insignificant variants.&amp;rsquo;&#xA;32 As pointed out above, his argument is that no real Kashmirian recension ever existed.&#xA;33 Note that Belvalkar (1941, pp. 25–6) does not consider the Kashmirian recension a regional one, but a Śaiva sectarian one. For more on this question, see Bansat-Boudon (2015, pp. 94-5).&#xA;34 On the history of this discovery, see Bansat-Boudon (2015, p. 92).&#xA;35 For numerous examples, see Schrader (1930, pp. 12ff.).&#xA;36&#xA;See Schrader (1930) and (1935), Edgerton (1932) and Belvalkar (1939, 1941, 1945). For more on this debate, see Bansat-Boudon (2015, pp. 93–5).&#xA;37 See Adluri-Bagchee (2016). The authors do admit that &amp;lsquo;a complete evaluation of Schrader&amp;rsquo;s claims is only possible by re-examining all his sources and comparing these with the editor&amp;rsquo;s decisions in the Critical Edition.&amp;rsquo; Perhaps because they do not intend to take up such a time-consuming task, they do not discuss any textual passages thoroughly from a philological point of view, and when they mention&#xA;SpringerAbhinavagupta on the Kashmirian Gītā&#xA;We do not consider it our task to take sides in this controversy, but, as we shall point out, we do think that at certain places the Kashmirian recension offers what appears to be an earlier version of the text than the Vulgate, without this being the case everywhere. What is certainly important for us is the existence of Schrader&amp;rsquo;s work, which, in addition to Lakshman Joo&amp;rsquo;s Gītā, gives us support when considering certain variants to be Kashmirian and helps us to reconstruct Abhinavagupta&amp;rsquo;s mūla. In addition to Schrader&amp;rsquo;s invaluable work on the Kashmirian recension, several other editions have proved to be helpful for the reconstruction of Abhinavagupta&amp;rsquo;s Gītā. Most importantly, the texts of two other early commentators who were Kashmirian or at least used some form of the Kashmirian Gītā must be taken into account. One is Bhaskara&amp;rsquo;s Bhagavadāśayānusaraṇa (available only for the first nine chapters), which may tentatively be dated to the 9th century. This Bhaskara is certainly identical with the one who also wrote a commentary on the Brahmasutra (Kato 2011), and it seems that his Gītā, although perhaps not fully agreeing with what may be called the Kashmirian recension, was certainly close to it in many important respects (for more discussion, see our Appendix).38 Because of Bhaskara&amp;rsquo;s relatively early date, and since he was possibly Kashmirian, his testimony is very important when reconstructing the Kashmirian recension. Unlike Abhinavagupta&amp;rsquo;s, his commentary is quite detailed and fills in the gaps wherever Abhinavagupta&amp;rsquo;s commentary is lacking or too concise to reconstruct his reading. We have consulted the only edition of the text published by Subhadra Jha (Benares, Varanaseya Sanskrit Vishvavidyalaya, 1965), of which a preliminary study had been provided by van Buitenen in the form of an article dated 1965. Curiously, although van Buitenen examined Bhaskara&amp;rsquo;s commentary on the Kashmirian Gītā and showed that its readings were better than those of the Vulgate, he adopts an ambiguous position when he translates the BhG (1981). He claims (p. xii) to follow Belvalkar&amp;rsquo;s critical edition, but to &amp;lsquo;have added occasional variant readings, for which there is better authority&amp;rsquo; and to &amp;lsquo;have appended in [his] textual notes a further list of readings based on the early commentary of Bhaskara.&amp;lsquo;39&#xA;Footnote 37 continued&#xA;variants, they dismiss them as irrelevant for the reader &amp;lsquo;using the text for self-reflection and selftransformation.&amp;rsquo;&#xA;38 On the question of the relation of Bhāskara&amp;rsquo;s Gītā and the Kashmirian Gītā, see van Buitenen (1965, p. 104), which, however, does not solve all the problems. He concludes that ‘for the Bhagavadgītā too the K[ashmirian] tradition carries on a text, however deteriorated here and there, that was authentic and of which we have the earliest record in Bhaskara&amp;rsquo;s bhāṣya.&amp;rsquo; See also our Appendix.&#xA;39 In fact, in his textual notes (p. 161) van Buitenen does not give any list of Bhaskara&amp;rsquo;s readings, but only refers to his 1965 paper &amp;lsquo;A Contribution to the Critical Edition of the Bhagavadgītā&amp;rsquo; and adds: &amp;lsquo;I have accepted into the text only those readings that make any difference in the translation.&amp;rsquo; However, in reality, van Buitenen retains very few of Bhaskara&amp;rsquo;s readings even when they would make a difference in the translation. He accepts, for instance, the transposition between Bhisma and Bhima in 1.10, ta eva naḥ sthita yoddhum prāṇāms tyaktvā sudustyajān (for the Vulgate&amp;rsquo;s ta ime &amp;lsquo;vasthita yuddhe prāṇāms tyaktvā dhanāni ca, on this reading, see below, note 46) in 1.33cd, paradharmodayad api (for the Vulgate&amp;rsquo;s paradharmo bhayāvahaḥ) in 3.35d, and vā &amp;lsquo;in the sense of iva&amp;rsquo; (for the Vulgate&amp;rsquo;s ca) in 3.39d. It is nevertheless rather puzzling that in his translation, van Buitenen does not retain the very first &amp;lsquo;Kashmirian&amp;rsquo; variant (1.1b), which is also read by Bhaskara, namely sarvakṣatrasamāgame (for the Vulgate&amp;rsquo;s samaveta yuyutsavaḥ), although van Buitenen (1965, p. 103) starts his list of Bhaskara&amp;rsquo;s variants with this one, observing that it is stylistically superior to the Vulgate&amp;rsquo;s version.&#xA;Springer&#xA;L. Bansat-Boudon, J. Törzsök&#xA;The other commentary is Ramakantha&amp;rsquo;s 40 Sarvatobhadra (950-1000), which is unambiguously of Kashmirian origin and is equally indispensable. Schrader was the first to have identified it in the form of a MS (MS 3271, Library of the India Office), dated 1750, written in Kashmirian nāgarī, and copied from an even older Saradā original (Schrader 1930, pp. 1-4, Chintamani 1941, p. xiii); and with the discovery of this commentary, he also launched the debate on the Kashmirian Gītā. We have consulted three editions of this text, published by S.N. Tadpatrikar (Poona 1939), T. R. Chintamani (Madras 1941), and Madhusudan Kaul Sastri (Srinagar 1943), of which Chintamani&amp;rsquo;s has proved to be the most faithful to Ramakaṇṭha&amp;rsquo;s commentary as well as to the Kashmirian Gītā (see at 2.5 discussed in note 59.) Ramakantha&amp;rsquo;s text is available for the whole Gītā, although his commentary is very succinct on the first chapter. His testimony is as valuable for the constitution of the Kashmirian recension as Bhaskara&amp;rsquo;s.&#xA;There exists a third published commentary on the Kashmirian Gītā: the Anandavardhini, written by Anandavardhana in Kashmir, in the 17th century. He should not be confused with the famous author of the Dhvanyaloka (9th century). Belvalkar published his commentary in 1941, which made him change his mind concerning the Kashmirian recension of the Gītā: he admits in his introduction that another version of the Gītā did exist, which was different from the Vulgate. He nevertheless sees it as a sectarian, Śaiva version rather than a regional, i.e. Kashmirian one. Since this commentary is much later than Abhinavagupta&amp;rsquo;s and was certainly more exposed to the influence of the Vulgate, we have decided not to use it for our edition in general, but to consult it only occasionally, to be in a better position to evaluate the transmission.&#xA;After establishing the external sources we may use in addition to Abhinavagupta&amp;rsquo;s commentary and the manuscript sources thereof, let us look at the different cases in which an editorial decision must be made as to which reading to accept. We have thus far encountered three different situations.&#xA;41&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FOREWORD</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/mahAbhAratam/vyAsaH/shlokashaH/bhagavad-gItA-parva/meta/abhinavagupta-gItArtha-sangrahaH/0/FOREWORD/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/mahAbhAratam/vyAsaH/shlokashaH/bhagavad-gItA-parva/meta/abhinavagupta-gItArtha-sangrahaH/0/FOREWORD/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;By Professor K. Satchidananda Murty&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;About 800 A.D. Vasugupta of Kashmir wrote explanatory verses on the Sivasūtra which was claimed to be Siva&amp;rsquo;s revelation. Somānanda (850 A.D.) in his Sivadrsti and other works developed Vasugupta&amp;rsquo;s ideas, and Utpala (c. 900 A.D.) in his Īsvarapratyabhijñākārikā logically co-ordinated these ideas and created God-non-dualism (Isvarādvaya vāda). Abhinavagupta (950-1000 A.D.) through his explanatory (Vimarsini) work on Utpala&amp;rsquo;s and his independent works (Paramārthasāra, Tantraloka, etc.) systematised the doctrines of this school. His disciple Kṣemarāja (975-1025 A.D.) also wrote some important works. Utpala and Abhinavagupta are two of the great thinkers of India. śaivism, Sūnyavāda, Buddhism and Advaita Vedānta influenced this school. What Gaudapāda was to Savkara&amp;rsquo;s Advaita, Sankaranandana (author of Prajñālankāra), some scholars say, was to Abhinavagupta&amp;rsquo;s Pratyabhijñā. Sankaranandana, it is conjectured, was a Buddhist who later became a śaiva, and he especially influe Aced Abhinavagupta&amp;rsquo;s theory of knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/mahAbhAratam/vyAsaH/shlokashaH/bhagavad-gItA-parva/meta/abhinavagupta-gItArtha-sangrahaH/0/INTRODUCTION/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/mahAbhAratam/vyAsaH/shlokashaH/bhagavad-gItA-parva/meta/abhinavagupta-gItArtha-sangrahaH/0/INTRODUCTION/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;धीनाम् अवित्री अवतु।&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Śrīmad Bhagavadgitā (BG) is well known to the world of scholars. It is the core-part of the Mahābhārata (MB) and is the most popular Indian philosophical work. For, it provides the aspirant with a practical manual in a simple language, show ing him the way how to live a calm life in the midst of the stresses and pulls of the extreme opposites of desire and hatred, pleasure and pain, joy and grief etc. etc,&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Van buitenen</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/mahAbhAratam/vyAsaH/shlokashaH/bhagavad-gItA-parva/meta/abhinavagupta-gItArtha-sangrahaH/0/van-buitenen/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/mahAbhAratam/vyAsaH/shlokashaH/bhagavad-gItA-parva/meta/abhinavagupta-gItArtha-sangrahaH/0/van-buitenen/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A Contribution to the Critical Edition of the Bhagavadgītā&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Author(s): J. A. B. van Buitenen&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Source: Journal of the American Oriental Society , Jan. - Mar., 1965, Vol. 85, No. 1&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(Jan. - Mar., 1965), pp. 99-109&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Published by: American Oriental Society&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Stable URL: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jstor.org/stable/597711&#34;&gt;https://www.jstor.org/stable/597711&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A CONTRIBUTION TO&#xA;THE CRITICAL EDITION OF THE BHAGAVADGĪTĀ&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;A NOTE ON BHAGAVADGĪTĀ 1.10.&#xA;J. A. B. VAN BUITENEN&#xA;UNIVERSITY OF CHICAGO&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;IN THE FIRST CHAPTER OF THE GITA occurs a stanza which has given the Indian commentators more trouble than modern interpreters have found with it. The stanza is spoken by Duryodhana:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>विषयसचिका</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/mahAbhAratam/vyAsaH/shlokashaH/bhagavad-gItA-parva/meta/abhinavagupta-gItArtha-sangrahaH/0/viShayasachikA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/mahAbhAratam/vyAsaH/shlokashaH/bhagavad-gItA-parva/meta/abhinavagupta-gItArtha-sangrahaH/0/viShayasachikA/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;समर्पणमा&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;प्रथमोऽध्यायः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;द्वितीयोऽध्यायः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;gilro105159 तृतीयोऽध्यायः&#xA;43 चतर्थोऽध्यायः&#xA;EDITE 1567 पञ्चमोऽध्यायः&#xA;87 षष्ठोऽध्यायः Sant&#xA;mitaasiriya 1000 सप्तमोऽध्यायः&#xA;tarinone 119 अष्ट मोऽध्यायः&#xA;11831&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;नवमोऽध्यायः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;-6805115310&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;दशमोऽध्यायः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;174 एकादशोऽध्यायः द्वादशोऽध्यायः&#xA;196&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;त्रयोदशोऽध्यायः&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;204 चतुर्दशोऽध्यायः&#xA;215 पञ्चदशोऽध्यायः&#xA;226 षोडशोऽध्यायः&#xA;239 सप्तदशोऽध्यायः viantart.itA&#xA;247 अष्टादशोऽध्यायः&amp;mdash;de अनुक्रमणिकाः mir&#xA;१. श्रीमद्भगवद्गीताश्लोकानामनुक्रमणिका&#xA;297 २. श्रीमद्भगवद्गीताश्लोकपाठभेदानामनुक्रमणिका&#xA;311 ३. अभिनवगुप्तपादीयश्लोकानामनुक्रमणिका&#xA;330 ४. आकरग्रन्थकतृनाम्नामनुक्रमणिका&#xA;330 ५. आकरग्रन्थनाम्नामनुक्रमणिका&#xA;डा&#xA;331 ६. विशेषशब्दानाम नुक्रमणिका&#xA;349&#xA;262&#xA;eft:&#xA;SRIMADBHAGAVADGITA&#xA;WITH&#xA;GITĀRTHASANGRAHA&#xA;OF&#xA;ABHINAVAGUPTA&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
