<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्-लेखाः on महाभारते विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/mahAbhAratam/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्-लेखाः on महाभारते विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 26 Dec 2013 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/mahAbhAratam/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>The successors of the kaunteya-s in the national memory of bhArata-s and bhoTa-s and related discursions</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/mahAbhAratam/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2013-12-26_the-successors-of-the-kaunteya-s-in-the-national-memory-of-bharata-s-and-bhota-s-and-related-discursions/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Dec 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/mahAbhAratam/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2013-12-26_the-successors-of-the-kaunteya-s-in-the-national-memory-of-bharata-s-and-bhota-s-and-related-discursions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2013/12/26/the-successors-of-the-kaunteya-s-in-the-national-memory-of-bharata-s-and-bhota-s-and-related-discursions/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/9CJ5Vhx1oEWbxbYLqklAlNMTjNZETYmyPJy0liipFm0?feat=embedwebsite&#34;&gt;&lt;figure class=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &lt;a href=&#34;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-poL9YmtTfgs/Uru9g_7rdSI/AAAAAAAACzY/6JeMO_NO2VY/s640/pandavas.jpg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&#xA;        &lt;img src=&#34;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-poL9YmtTfgs/Uru9g_7rdSI/AAAAAAAACzY/6JeMO_NO2VY/s640/pandavas.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &#xA;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;epic&#34;&gt;Epic&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;As per the mahAbharata, the great war on the kuru field came to a&#xA;conclusion with the smashing of duryodhana’s thighs by bhIma. While&#xA;balarAma wanted to kill bhIma for unfairly defeating the kuru prince in&#xA;the gadAyuddha, kR^iShNa convinced him to refrain from doing so.&#xA;Thereafter, he led the surviving pANDu-s and his relative sAtyaki to&#xA;rest in the enemy camp. But the remaining survivors on the pANDu side&#xA;slept in their own camp. Late that night, ashvatthAman, having been&#xA;inspired by an owl hunting sleeping crows, attacked the pANDava camp&#xA;aided by his uncle kR^ipa and yadu hero kR^itavarman. There he killed&#xA;the sleeping pA~nchAla princes shikhaNDin, dR^iShTadyumna, yudhAmanyu&#xA;and uttamaujas by kicking them or strangling them with bowstrings. Then&#xA;he killed and beheaded the 5 sons of draupadI: prativindhya, sutasoma,&#xA;shrutakIrti, shatAnIka and shrutakarman. With that the line of the&#xA;illustrious pa~nchAla-s, which was praised in the veda, came to an end.&#xA;The pANDu-s were left with draupadI, who represented the “shrI” of the&#xA;erstwhile pa~nchAla realm.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Theories for the bhArata conundrum</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/mahAbhAratam/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-05-05_theories-for-the-bharata-conundrum/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 May 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/mahAbhAratam/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-05-05_theories-for-the-bharata-conundrum/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2006/05/05/theories-for-the-bharata-conundrum/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We earlier described the major problem termed the bhArata conundrum,&#xA;where we notice a silence regarding the pANDavas alone in the vedic&#xA;textual layers, but they are prominently mentioned in all the later&#xA;texts of Sanskrit and prakrit literature. The following plausible&#xA;theories may be cited in this regard:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The vedic authors were of the kaurava party and hence purposely&#xA;omitted references to the pANDus. The main problem with this theory is&#xA;why do they mention the descendents of the pANDava-s as per the great&#xA;epic in very positive light. In fact they do refer to dR^itarAShTra&#xA;vaichitravIrya in negative light, just as the surviving version of the&#xA;epic. They also refer to the pa~nchalas like shikhaNDin in positive&#xA;light.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2) Generational difference theory: The people with the same names as&#xA;the mahabhArata characters are in fact people of an earlier generation,&#xA;coincidentally having same names as the epic characters. While there is&#xA;some evidence for this from the paurANic genealogies, the patronymics&#xA;typically only match the characters of the great epic.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The mystery of the pANDava-s</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/mahAbhAratam/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-05-04_the-mystery-of-the-pandava-s/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 May 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/mahAbhAratam/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-05-04_the-mystery-of-the-pandava-s/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2006/05/04/the-mystery-of-the-pandava-s/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;While the bhArata epic is a central to understanding the rise of the&#xA;Indian state and the very culture of the Indian people, there are some&#xA;mysterious issues associated with it which still leave a major gap in&#xA;understanding this historical period. At its heart the epic represents&#xA;the expansion of the kuru-pA~nchAla realm over the whole of Northern&#xA;India, establish a unified administrative and cultural zone. The&#xA;sequence of events leading to this as painted in the mbh are thus: 1) We&#xA;have the rise of the bhAratas under their eponymous founder the great&#xA;conqueror bharata daushyanti who raises this line of the pUru kShatriya&#xA;clan to prominence and pre-eminent rulers amongst the Indo-Aryans. 2)&#xA;The dynastic successors of bharata daushyanti (not necessarily his&#xA;biological lineage descendent) split up into two powerful states&#xA;(subsequently the kuru and the pa~nchala) at the time of the brothers&#xA;purumIDha and ajAmIDha. 3) The kuru and the pa~nchala were the&#xA;pre-eminent rulers of much of north India jostling for territory with&#xA;each other, as well as other Indo-Aryan states. 4) The period of the&#xA;great bhArata war, where through marital alliances with pa~nchala,&#xA;virATa, yAdava and other smaller Aryan states a younger branch of the&#xA;kuru-s, the pANDava-s, overthrew their older cousins the main-line&#xA;kaurava-s. In the bloody bhArata war most north Indian rulers were&#xA;annihilated, giving the surviving pA~NDava-s total control of much of&#xA;this swath of land. Subsequently, their successor janamejaya pArIkShita&#xA;through a formal ashvamedha rite and the sarpa sattra marking the&#xA;destruction the nAga rivals made himself the emperor of the first&#xA;unified empire of India, marking the efflorescence of the formal shrauta&#xA;period of vedic culture.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The fall of asura prahlAda</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/mahAbhAratam/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-08-07_the-fall-of-prahlada/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Aug 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/mahAbhAratam/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2005-08-07_the-fall-of-prahlada/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2005/08/07/the-fall-of-prahlada/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;prahlAda, the demoniac son of hiraNyakashipu, ascended the throne of the asuras after his father had been slain by nR^isimha. Spreading fear and havoc in the in the worlds due to his pride and immense strength he caused much anxiety to the gods. It was then that the young kumAra, the commander of the deva army, filled with youthful pride decided to display his sports. He threw his shakti and pierced the earth with it. He then posed a challenge to the universe by stating:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>IA-motifs</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/mahAbhAratam/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/IA-motifs/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/mahAbhAratam/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/IA-motifs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://unrollthread.com/t/1599122000198266881/&#34;&gt;TW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Reg. long thread pertaining to Alonso&amp;rsquo;s work. I sort of feel induced to comment.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I think what Alonso has noticed are mostly not specific similarities between the Mbh &amp;amp; Greek epic &amp;ndash; what in biology we would call synapomorphies. Rather they are motifs from the ancient IE past that are widely spread across the IE mythosphere. What they illustrate is that certain motifs were common to ancestral IE epic traditions &amp;amp; new historical events were fitted into these old thematic &amp;ldquo;wave-guides.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Locii</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/mahAbhAratam/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/locii/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/mahAbhAratam/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/locii/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.scribblemaps.com/maps/view/mahAbhArata/vMPwBxmc18&#34;&gt;map&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Southern recensions mention groups like kerala/cherapada, choLa &amp;amp; pANDya. However, northern ones do not. andhra seems more universal &amp;ndash; the fighter chANUra or his aid killed by devakIputra was an andhra. Location of andhra was probably south of kali~Nga but a bit unclear to me.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Not central to the map but more related to below discussion. If we for a moment just include everything, i.e., don&amp;rsquo;t make an attempt a priori to distinguish interpolations from the core Mbh (leave aside the &amp;ldquo;critical&amp;rdquo;= Pune edition) we have following counts for &amp;ldquo;distant&amp;rdquo; peoples&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>V1 frequencies</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/mahAbhAratam/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/v1-frequencies/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/mahAbhAratam/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/v1-frequencies/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Frequency of mention of some common v1 clans in the total mahAbharata&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;table&gt;&#xA;  &lt;thead&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;th&gt;Clan&lt;/th&gt;&#xA;          &lt;th&gt;Number&lt;/th&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;  &lt;/thead&gt;&#xA;  &lt;tbody&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;a~ngiras&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;119&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;bhArgava&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;259&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;bhR^igu&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;240&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;bharadvAja&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;375&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;gotama&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;179&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;kashyapa&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;266&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;kaushika&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;114&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;parAshara&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;89&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;vasiShTha&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;274&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;vishvAmitra&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;186&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;  &lt;/tbody&gt;&#xA;&lt;/table&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
