<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;देवबोध-ज्ञान-दीपिका on महाभारते विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/mahAbhAratam/vyAsaH/devabodha-jnAna-dIpikA/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;देवबोध-ज्ञान-दीपिका on महाभारते विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/mahAbhAratam/vyAsaH/devabodha-jnAna-dIpikA/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>आदिपर्व</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/mahAbhAratam/vyAsaH/devabodha-jnAna-dIpikA/Adiparva/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/mahAbhAratam/vyAsaH/devabodha-jnAna-dIpikA/Adiparva/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[ज्ञानदीपिका (महाभरते आदिपर्व)&#x9;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ebharatisampat.in/readbook3.php?bookid=MjgxODYxMDUxMzU3Mzg1&amp;amp;pageno=MjI0MjQyNjk5NTk=&#34;&gt;EB&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;\&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;श्रीदेवबोधकृतमहाभारततात्पर्यटीका&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ज्ञानदीपिका&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;महाभारते आदिपर्व&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;—————&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Commentary by Devabodha on the Adiparvan&lt;br&gt;&#xA;of the Mahabharata&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Edited by&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;R. N. Dandekar&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Bhandarkar Oriental Research Institate&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;POONA&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1941&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;INTRODUCTION&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(1) Dr. V. S. SUKTHANKAR has [proved&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; that the Jnanadipika, Mahabharata-tatparyatika, by Devabodha is the oldest commentary extant on the Mahabharata. As such it is most valuable both for the understanding and the constitution of the text of the Great Epic. Devabodha&amp;rsquo;s commentary is far superior to Nilakantha&amp;rsquo;s, which is in common use and which is almost the latest commentary on the Mahabharata, belonging as it does to the last quarter of the 17th century. Unlike other commentaries, the Jñanadipika is a concisetikā; as a rule, it explains only the difficult words and passages in the text. But &amp;ldquo;occasionally it offers explanations of constructional obscurities and grammatical difficulties, and gives the gist of the passages; in the latter case, usually, under the citation of entire verses (i. e. half ślokas) from the text&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&amp;rdquo; Devabodha was a well-known and highly respected Samnyasi, having the title Paramahamsa Parivrajakacarya, and his commentary has been cited with approval—nay with great reverence—by all subsequent commentators like Arjunamiśra, Sarvajñanārāyaṇa and Nilakantha among others. In fact, Arjunamiśra has based his commentary largely on that of Devabodha. Not only has Arjunamiśra given long extracts from the Jñanadipika, but he has also copied very large portions from it verbalim. In the opinion of Dr. SUKTHANKAR &amp;ldquo;the Arthadipika may be considered as a revised and enlarged edition of the Jñanadipika&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&amp;ldquo;Important readings from the commentary of Devabodha have been cited in the Critical Edition of the Mahabharata ( Ed ), which is being published by the Bhandarkar Oriental Research Institute&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, however, tend to show that the version of Devabodha was of the Sarada-K type.&amp;rdquo;).For these reasons the commentary is considered to be eminently worthy of publication and the portion&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>भीष्म-पर्व</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/mahAbhAratam/vyAsaH/devabodha-jnAna-dIpikA/bhIShma-parva/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/mahAbhAratam/vyAsaH/devabodha-jnAna-dIpikA/bhIShma-parva/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[ज्ञानदीपिका&#x9;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ebharatisampat.in/readbook3.php?bookid=MjE1NDA4MzkwMzkxNTg1&amp;amp;pageno=MjI0MjQyNjk5NTk=&#34;&gt;EB&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[TABLE]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[TABLE]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;INTRODUCTION&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The present edition of Devabodha&amp;rsquo;s Commentary on the Bhişmaparvan is based upon a solitary MS. of it, being No. 12982 of the Baroda Oriental Institute, bearing the date Śaka 1688 (A. D. 1766). The MS. consists of two parts. The first contains five folios (fol. la being blank), and carries the text from the beginning of the parvan up to the end of adhyāya 22 of the Critical Edition. Then there is a blank folio after which, with a fresh pagination and in a different handwriting, are given foll. 1-9 (fol. 3b, ta, 9a being left blank ) containing the text from Critical Edition adhyāya 41. st. 1 up to the end of the parvan. Thus there is missing the entire commentary on the Bhagavadgita. We have, however, found, in another MS., what is stated to be Devabodha&amp;rsquo;s commentary on certain stanzas of the Bhagavadgita. But nothing definite can be said of its authenticity.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;That Devabodha is the earliest known Mahabharata commentator is admitted by all, he being quoted by Nilakantha (cir. 1680–1693 A. D.)¹, Arjunamiśra (cir 1450- 1500 A, D), Sarvajna-Nārāyaṇa (of the 13th century A.D., if identical with the commentator on the Manusmrti)³. and Vimalabodha (between 1150 and 1300 A. D.). The value of the commentary for a critical constitution of the&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
